[SPEAKER_00]: So, Bhante, what is the difference between hīrī and uttapa versus just kind of an ambiguous hindrance of guilt?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, why would guilt be a hindrance?
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it would be a hindrance if it's with regard to things that you don't have to be guilty about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I mean, just take a random example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say you feel guilty about not killing in a certain instance where it would have been... it would have made your life better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, that's an extreme example, but it's an unambiguous one, where guilt would actually be obscuring
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you need to see?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, there's a reason why the suttas always say that all these wholesome factors, all these qualities of mind that you have to develop, they depend on right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't just kind of... you can't have faith in random things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have shame and remorse in regard to random things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be mindful of random things.
[SPEAKER_01]: compose your mind, random things, and understand random things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those five faculties have to be guided by right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to then learn what the criteria are to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, eh... breaking precepts is what you have to be ashamed of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eh... but you will only be able to arrive at the right shame if you understand why breaking precepts is harmful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you have a goal,
[SPEAKER_01]: That you have to fulfill and then regard even if it's a worldly goal, actually, and then you find yourself doing things that lead against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The natural result of that is guilt.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even something you have to fabricate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just feel like, oh, I wanted this and I did the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to then understand to be able to to have that actual sense of shame.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not just a random fabricated thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to
[SPEAKER_01]: I have developed that connection between breaking the precepts and going against my goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that connection needs to be clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're still in doubt that, oh, maybe sometimes it's not an issue, maybe sometimes the benefit outweighs the harm, then you won't be able to feel ashamed on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to be, basically, the connection needs to be inseparable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where you're unable to doubt that if you do these things, you are going against the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if that perspective is established, the shame will arise naturally.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would then need to cover it up, not to have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, well, how do you establish that perspective?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have to contemplate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, most people would only see the secondary consequences of why breaking precepts would be harmful.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would see, oh, well, it leads to the harm of others.
[SPEAKER_01]: It kind of creates trouble for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: leads to, I don't know, loss of wealth, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to see... you want to understand it in such a way that you couldn't, even in the most fortunate circumstance, even if you actually end up helping everyone, including yourself, and producing nothing but gain, that even then, doing these things would be harmful for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only way to understand that is by understanding greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing those as internal things, that basically you're chaining yourself to, simply by committing these actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like a curse that you're putting on yourself, that even though, regardless of anything else you might do,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're training yourself to crave for pleasant feeling, training yourself to crave against pleasant feeling, training yourself to resist lack of activity, which means that's going to come back and bite you either late... well, not only come back and bite you right now, cultivating those tendencies is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, don't break precepts after you broke precepts, and you will see that your mind was already
[SPEAKER_01]: In a bad state, it was simply being covered up by the all the distractions you were engaging with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will then realize having this, regardless of what else happens, having this mental state is harmful in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you start making that inseparable connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yeah, all the other stuff remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to deny it that sometimes breaking precepts could lead to mundane benefits.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like killing, in some instance, you could... Well, nobody would do it if it didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you could save millions of lives by killing one person, factually.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, none of that will be able to override the perspective of what you're actually doing on that internal level when you decide to kill.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you should try to make that your metric, rather than just guilt about this or that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like I said, when that connection is established, when you see yourself chaining yourself to these unpleasant mental states, automatically, by doing these actions, you won't be able to not feel guilt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's like, who would knowingly harm themselves?
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever somebody goes and does something that's harmful, it's because they were focused on the gratifying aspect of that action.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't do something while at the same time being prioritizing the perception of danger in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that is what you put forward,
[SPEAKER_01]: The perception of danger that is independent of any circumstances, that cannot change no matter what happens externally, then you can't but feel guilt.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't but be rightly apprehensive, which is the one translation for uttapa, like apprehension of wrongdoing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be able to not feel that in regard to those actions, because it would be obvious the harm is what's being highlighted, is what's being put first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you are feeling guilty and its reference point is your idea of what the practice is, does that make it always a good metric?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to first clarify those ideas about what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, for example, some people might feel guilty about not meditating.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's
[SPEAKER_01]: That implies a wrong view of what the practice is, because it's prioritizing this random observance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, what you would have to be ashamed of is, am I engaging with greed aversion and delusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, many people would have that upside down.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would be more ashamed of not meditating, than they would be about not being celibate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no way to get around the need to clarify your views and clarify what you're actually trying to develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you can't have right intention without right view first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to clarify what nibbāna is, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what is the liberation that you're striving for?
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people have
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an event that can happen to you or not happen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, you would be
[SPEAKER_01]: Ashamed of not doing these random things that could have led to it by some unknown connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, if you understood that literally, as the Buddha said, says it, nibbāna is the freedom from greed, aversion and delusion, from lust, aversion and ignorance, you you wouldn't be able to not be ashamed of actual lust, aversion and ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And being... yeah, being ashamed of these other things, because of your unclarified, misguided ideas about what practices, would actively take away from the right shame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can't be ashamed of both relevant and irrelevant things at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if... even if you were to, let's say, never break a precept, but your criteria for shame isn't in that area,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when you break precepts, or if you were to break precepts, you would end up finding excuses, kind of absolving yourself from the issue, saying, oh, well, you know, I can always do better next time.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't allow yourself to feel that as, oh, categorically, I should not have done that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't, if that's not what's going to happen, then even if you don't end up breaking precepts, you're not headed in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it means you're not, again, without right view, without having the right perspective of what is wholesome and unwholesome, nothing else can be practiced.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a sutra where the Buddha says that, when somebody starts with wrong intention, whatever they do, sorry, with wrong view, whatever they do, by body, speech or mind, is polluted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why external adherence to the precepts is not really the criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's whether... Would you...
[SPEAKER_01]: Ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you, in every possible instance where you intentionally broke a precept, feel ashamed?
[SPEAKER_01]: If there's an instance where that wouldn't be the case, then your idea of what practice is, is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's taking you in a different direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would just be trying to cover up the shame that you would feel on account of breaking the precept, which seems like... You may not even see it as cover-up.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you're just looking elsewhere as your goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you feel ashamed of not living up to that wrong goal that has nothing to do with what the Buddhist practice actually is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not really a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, if you have the right aim,
[SPEAKER_01]: Shame, in regard to going against that aim, is natural.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something you have to fabricate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, if you feel shame in regard to that, well, how do you make sure that it doesn't go overboard?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, ask yourself, what is your shame leading to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, is it fortifying your intention to never engage in those actions again?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it kind of making you feel like it doesn't really matter because you're worthless?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you're kind of just leaning towards self-loathing?
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's the case, then that's not actual guilt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if it's if it's the real guilt that that is hīryōtapa, that the Buddha described as the protectors of the world, then it couldn't possibly be leading you in the direction of transgression, in the direction of doing it again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like... it would always be taking you in the direction of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Not repeating those actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why the Buddha didn't say, monks, be careful of shame and remorse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't cultivate shame and remorse too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, it was... those are two of the five faculties, that if a noble disciple cultivates, they will become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the same level, in fact more primordial, than mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Samādhi and wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're not ashamed of the right things, your mindfulness is just directed at other random things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to be directed at, I should never engage with greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not having that mindfulness, you couldn't possibly achieve the right composure, which is a mind free from greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And without right composure, you couldn't possibly achieve the right understanding, which will make you incapable of doing those things again, once and for all.